Guide to the Ivan Morris Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Ivan Morris Papers,
1931-1976
Morris, Ivan I.
18 linear ft. (ca. 18,900 items in 47 boxes and 3 volumes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079561
Biographical Note
Ivan Ira Esme Morris, 1925-1976, was chairman of Columbia's East Asian Department from 1966-1969.
Scope and Content
Correrspondence, manuscripts, notes, memoranda, documents, photographs and printed materials. In addition to personal correspondence and documents, there are files of Amnesty International, the human rights organization of which Morris was American Section chairman. Also included are notes and manuscripts of Morris' studies in Japanese literature and culture, particularly relating to his many books and translations. His interest in puzzles, and compilations of several volumes of them, are reflected in notes and correspondence. Among the major correspondence are Donald Keene, Anthony Powell, Sacheverell Sitwell and Arthur Waley.
1984 addition: Diaries, correspondence, manuscripts, and audio tapes
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 8 series:
Series I: Personal Files
Series II: Miscellaneous Files
Series III: Books
Series IV: Oversize
Series V: 1980 Addition
Series VI: 1982 Addition
Series VII: 1984 Addition
Series VIII: 2003 Addition
Subjects
Amnesty International.; Columbia University.--East Asian Institute.; Keene, Donald.; Waley, Arthur.; Powell, Anthony, 1905-2000.; Sitwell, Sacheverell, 1897-1988.; Japan--Social life and customs.; Japanese literature.; Japanese literature--Translations into English.; Puzzles.; Albums.; Articles.; Audio tapes.; Bylaws.; Calling cards.; Contracts.; Diaries.; Indexes.; Lecture notes.; Lectures.; Memoranda.; Minutes.; Notebooks.; Obituaries.; Passports.; Photographs.; Proofs.; Reviews.; Scrapbooks.; Statutes.; College teachers.; Scholars.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 2-47. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Selected family correspondence is closed.
Acquisition
1979 M-1979 Papers Alexander, Annalita M. Gift
Gift of Annalita M. Alexander, 1979, 1980, 1982 & 1984.
- Series I: Personal Files
  - Subseries 1.1: Cataloged Correspondence
    - Acton, Harold To Ivan Morris, Florence, 2 Jan. 1971, (4 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
    - Baldwin, Roger Nash To Ivan Morris, [v.p.], May-Nov. 1974, (2 t.l.s. (with related correspondence) ) (Box 1)
    - Barzun, Jacques To Ivan Morris, New York, 8 Nov. 1968, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
    - Boyle, Kay To Ivan Morris, San Francisco, Cal., 1975-1976, (1 a.l.s. 1, t.l.s.) (Box 1)
    - Compton-Burnett, Ivy To Ivan Morris, London, 27 Nov. 1967, (1 page a.l.s. (on card, with copy of related letter) ) (Box 1)
    - Forster, E[dward] M[organ], 1879-1970 To Ivan Morris, Cambridge, U.K., 31 Nov. 1967, (1 page ms.l.s. (with autograph postscript; with copy of related letter) ) (Box 1)
    - Gilliatt, Penelope To Ivan Morris, New York, 2 July 1976, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 1)
    - [Hazzard], Shirley To Ivan Morris, [v.p.], 1975-1976, (1 t.l.s. 1, a.l.s. (with envelope) ) (Box 1)
    - Janeway, Elizabeth To Ivan Morris, New York, 24 March 1976, (3 page t.l. (photostatic copy) ) (Box 1)
    - Keene, Donald To Ivan Morris, [v.p.], [n.d.] & 1961-1975, (8 a.l.s. 3, t.l.s. (with related correspondence) 1, Christmas card ) (Box 1)
    - Knopf, Alfred A. To Ivan Morris, New York, 24 Feb. 1967, (1 page t.l. (signed by secretary) ) (Box 1)
    - Knopf, Blanche W. To Ivan Morris, New York, 28 Nov. 1955, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 1)
    - Komroff, Manuel To Ivan Morris, Woodstock, N.Y., 27 Feb. 1968, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 1)
    - Laughlin, James To Ivan Morris, New York, 25 June 1964, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 1)
    - Mishima, Yukio To Ivan Morris, Tokyo, Jan.-Nov. 1970, (2 a.l.s. (with envelopes; photocopies) ) (Box 1)
    - Mishima, Yukio To Harold, [n.p.], 17 Nov. 1970, (1 page a.l.s. (photocopy) ) (Box 1)
    - Mishima, Mrs. Yukio To Ivan Morris, Tokyo, 21 June 1971, (3 page a.l.s. (written in Japanese with envelope; photocopy) ) (Box 1)
      [Correspondence in Japanese]
    - Morris, Ira To Ivan Morris, Agadir, Morocco, 2 March 1953, (3 page t.l.s. (with envelope) ) (Box 1)
    - Morris, Ira and Edita To, Nesles, France, 1968, (1 Christmas card ) (Box 1)
    - Powell, Anthony To Ivan Morris, Frome, U.K., 17 July 1964 & 6 Nov. 1967, (2 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
    - Riesman, David To Ivan Morris, Cambridge, Mass., 18 Aug. 1965, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 1)
    - Shawn, William To Ivan Morris, New York, 25 July 1975, (1 page t.l.s. (photostatic copy) ) (Box 1)
    - Sitwell, Sacheverell To Ivan Morris, Towcester, U.K., 1967-1968, (7 a.l.s. (with related correspondence) 3, a.p.c.s. (signed with initials; with related correspondence) ) (Box 1)
    - Steegmuller, Francis To Ivan Morris, New York, 5 Dec. 1971, (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
    - Stokes, Henry Scott To Ivan Morris, Tokyo, 28 Nov. 1970, (10 page t.l.s. (photocopy) ) (Box 1)
      [Re: Yukio Mishima]
    - [Trevor-Roper], Hugh [Redwald, 1914- ] To Ivan Morris, [n.p.], [n.d.], (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
    - [Trevor-Roper], Hugh [Redwald, 1914- ] To Roderick MacFarquhar, Oxford, U.K., 16 Nov. 1968, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 1)
    - Waley, Arthur To Theodore de Bary, London, 13 Jan. 1962, (1 page t.l.) (Box 1)
    - Waley, Arthur [David] To Ivan Morris, [London], [n.d.], (3 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
    - Waley, Arthur David and Alison Grant Robinson To Ivan Morris, London, ca. 26 May 1966, (1 page a.l.s. (on verso of marriage announcement; in hand of Alison Grant Robinson Waley; signed "A & A") ) (Box 1)
    - Waugh, Alec To Ivan Morris, Tangier, Morocco, 23 July 1975, (1 page a.l.s. (with envelope) ) (Box 1)
  - Subseries I.2: Uncataloged Correspondence
    - General, (2 folders ) (Box 1)
    - Legal correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - Family correspondence (RESTRICTED) (Box 1)
      [RESTRICTED]
  - Subseries I.3: Manuscripts and Documents
    - Forrestal, James, Washington, D.C., 9 Dec. 1944, (1 page p.d.s. (commission of Ivan Ira Morris as Ensign in the U.S. Navy) ) (Box 1)
    - Forrestal, James, Washington, D.C., 8 July 1946, (1 page p.d.s. (certificate of Satisfactory Service of Ivan Ira Morris in the U.S. Navy) ) (Box 1)
    - Keene, Donald [In Your Distant Street Few Drums Were Heard], [n.p.], ca. 1967, (12 page t.ms.s. (essay with autograph and manuscript corrections) ) (Box 1)
      [Essay included in Madly Singing in the Mountains by Ivan Morris]
    - Keene, Donald, [n.p.], [ca. March 1968], (1 page t.d.s. (assignment of copyright) ) (Box 1)
    - Morris, Ivan Misunderstandings re Mishima Suicide, [n.p.], [1970], (4 page a.ms. (essay; photocopy) ) (Box 1)
    - Sitwell, Sacheverell Reminiscences of Arthur Waley, [n.p.], ca. 1968, (4 page a.ms.s. (with four page typed copy, with autograph corrections) ) (Box 1)
    - Sitwell, Sacheverell, [n.p.], ca. 1968, (1 page t.d.s. (assignment of copyright) ) (Box 1)
  - Subseries I.4: Miscellaneous Files
    - Academic Record Philips Academy and Harvard University (Box 1)
    - Alexander, Annalita M. The Grinding Machine (Box 1)
    - Curriculum Vitae and Obituary (Box 1)
    - Jobs and Tenure (Box 1)
    - Jordan, C. Manuscripts (Box 2)
    - Memberships (Box 2)
    - Nationality (Box 2)
    - Notes, Manuscripts and Documents, Miscellaneous; 1975 Datebook (Box 2)
    - Obituaries and Memorials (Box 2)
    - Passports, (7 ) (Box 2)
    - School notebooks, Summerfields, Oxon, U.K., (3 volumes ) (Box 2)
    - Travel (Box 2)
    - U. S. Navy (Box 2)
  - Subseries I.5: Puzzles
    - Correspondence, notes and drafts related primarily to Morris' books The Lonely Monk and Other Puzzles and Basil the Bookworm and Other Puzzles (Box 3)
  - Subseries I.6: Amnesty International
    - Correspondence: General (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 4)
    - General (Box 4)
    - Board of Directors (Box 4)
    - Board of Directors: Minutes (Box 4)
    - Budget and Finances (Box 4)
    - By-Laws, Statutes, Incorporation (Box 4)
    - Executive Committee: Minutes (Box 4)
    - Executive Director (Box 4)
    - Fund-Raising (Box 5)
    - Fund-Raising: Art for Amnesty (Box 5)
    - Impartiality (Box 5)
    - Index to Minutes of the Board and Executive Committee Meetings (Box 5)
    - International Council and International Secretariat (Box 5)
    - Lobbying (Box 5)
    - Riverside Group (Box 5)
    - Staff (Box 5)
    - Missions and Investigations: China; Cuba; Dominican Republic; India; Iran; Japan; Syria/Israel; Urugay (Box 6)
    - Missions: General (Box 6)
    - Reports: General (Box 6)
    - Printed material: General, (2 folders ) (Box 7)
    - Printed material: Clippings (Box 7)
    - Printed material: Periodicals (Box 7)
  - Subseries I.7: Japanese Literature and Culture
    - Genji: Notes and Related material, (2 folders ) (Box 8)
    - Madly Singing in the Mountains: Correspondence, Notes, and Related Material (Box 8)
      [Book about Arthur Waley]
    - Madly Singing in the Mountains: Correspondence, Notes, and Related Material (Box 9)
    - Mishima, Yukio Correspondence and notes about, etc., (1 folder ) (Box 10)
    - The Nobility of Failure, (t.ms.) (Box 10)
    - The Nobility of Failure, (t.ms.) (Box 11)
    - The Pillow Book of Sei Shonagon: Notes, Manuscripts, and Related Material (Box 12)
    - Politics: Notes, Manuscripts, Correspondence, and Related Material (Box 13)
    - Morris, Ivan The Style of Murassaki Shikibu, (Dissertation - 2 volumes ) (Box 14)
    - Class Notes (Box 15)
    - Notes on the 17th Century, (2 folders ) (Box 15)
    - Notes on Women (Box 15)
    - Notes, (10 volumes of manuscript notebooks ) (Box 16)
    - Notes, (6 volumes of manuscript notebooks ) (Box 17)
    - Book Reviews (Box 18)
    - Nosca, Peter Manuscript (Box 18)
    - Sakamoto, Mariai Manuscripts and notes (Box 18)
    - Translations and miscellaneous notes (Box 18)
    - Notebooks and miscellaneous notes (Box 18)
      [Gift 1982]
    - Translation: Notes and Correspondence, (1 folder ) (Box 19)
    - Translation: Printed, (1 folder ) (Box 19)
    - Morris, Ivan Articles and Lectures (Box 19)
    - Morris, Ivan Miscellaneous notes and manuscripts (Box 19)
    - Clippings and articles by Ivan Morris (Box 20)
    - Clippings and articles - miscellaneous (Box 20)
- Series II: Miscellaneous Files
  - Subseries II.1: Photographs
    - Akayo (Box 21)
    - Family and personal (Box 21)
    - Japan, 1956-1959; 1973 (Feb.); 1973-1974 (Box 21)
    - Krementz, Jill (Box 21)
    - Mishima, Yukio (Box 21)
    - Morris, Ivan (Box 21)
    - Nehru, Bhutto (Box 21)
    - Macmillan, Harold (Box 21)
    - The Nobility of Failure (Box 21)
    - Nobuko (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous, (2 folders ) (Box 21)
  - Subseries II.2: Scrapbooks and Printed
    - Scrapbooks, (2 volumes ) (Box 22)
    - Printed, miscellaneous (Box 22)
    - Printed and miscellaneous material (Box 22)
- Series III: Books
  - Morris, Ira and Edita Books by Ira and Edita Morris (Box 23)
  - Morris, Edita Books by Edita Morris (Box 24)
  - Morris, Ivan Books by Ivan Morris (Box 25-27)
  - Morris, Ivan Books and printed (Japanese and miscellaneous). (Box 28)
- Series IV: Oversize
  - Harvard One document (Box 339)
  - Reviews of Morris' books and related items [Volumes 1 and 2], (2 scrapbooks ) (Box 338)
  - Reviews of Morris' books and related items [Volume 3], (1 scrapbook ) (Box 339)
  - The Tale of Genji Scroll, (1 paste-up volume ) (Box 337)
- Series V: 1980 Addition
  - Subseries V.1: Personal Files
    - General correspondence, 1971-1976 (Box 29)
    - Correspondence relating to Columbia University and jobs (Box 29)
    - Alexander, Annalita M. Miscellaneous items (Box 29)
    - Biographical material (Box 29)
    - Calling Cards (Box 29)
    - Contracts and Royalties (Box 29)
    - Family and personal documents (Box 29)
    - Miscellaneous items (Box 29)
  - Subseries V.2: Amnesty International
    - Amnesty International Miscellaneous materials (Box 29)
  - Subseries V.3: Japanese Literature and Culture
    - Columbia University Lecture notes (2 binders); Student papers (11); Miscellaneous (Box 30)
    - Morris, Ivan Book reviews; Lectures; Nobility of Failure (drafts and related items) (Box 31)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 31)
    - Notes and note cards (Box 32)
  - Subseries V.4: Miscellaneous Files
    - Photographs (Box 33)
    - Printed proofs, reviews, and miscellaneous (Box 33)
- Series VI: 1982 Addition
  - Photograph albums (including Margot Fonteyn in Japan) (Box 34)
  - Morris, Ira and Edita Correspondence, [v.p.], 1943-1973 (Box 35)
    [CLOSED]
  - Morris, Nubko Divorce (Box 35)
- Series VII: 1984 Addition
  - Subseries VII.1: Diaries
    - Diaries, 1945-1948 (Box 36)
  - Subseries VII.2: Personal Correspondence
    - Alexander, Annalita M. (Box 37)
    - Brazin, Anne (Box 37)
    - Cowan, J.S. (Box 37)
    - Crewe, Martha (Box 37)
    - Eissler, K.R. (Box 37)
    - Gentleman, Vivian F. (Box 37)
    - George, Ivan (Box 37)
    - Good, Jack (Box 37)
    - Harshell, Arnald (Box 37)
    - Keene, Donald (Box 37)
    - Kiddo, Anson (Box 37)
    - Lewis, Arne (Box 37)
    - MacGregor, Robert M. (Box 37)
    - Maclennar, Bud (Box 37)
    - Mason, Richard (Box 37)
    - Monet, Dorothy (Box 37)
    - Morris, Anne Wade (Box 37)
    - Morris, Ayako Ojawe (Box 37)
    - Morris, Nobuko (Box 37)
    - Poalazzi, Isabella (Box 37)
    - Letters (first names only) (Box 37)
    - Postcards (Box 37)
  - Subseries VII.3: Family Correspondence
    - Family correspondence (Mother, Father, Grandmother) (Box 38)
  - Subseries VII.4: Notes, etc.
    - Notes, manuscripts, business papers, and printed materials (Box 39)
  - Subseries VII.5: Audio
    - Broadcasts, speeches, and interviews (Box 40)
    - Portrait (Box 14/16/04)
- Series VIII: 2003 Addition
  Includes materials from 1999 gift
  - Subseries VIII.1: Restricted Correspondence
    - Ivan Morris Personal Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 41)
      [RESTRICTED ]
    - Mishima, Yukio To Ivan Morris, Tokyo, Jan.-Nov. 1970, (2 a.l.s. (with envelopes) ) (Box 41)
    - Mishima, Mrs. Yukio To Ivan Morris, Tokyo, 21 June 1971, (3 page a.l.s. (written in Japanese; with envelope) ) (Box 41)
      [RESTRICTED. Correspondence in Japanese]
    - Stokes, Henry Scott To Ivan Morris, Tokyo, 28 Nov. 1970, (10 page t.l.s. (re: Yukio Mishima) ) (Box 41)
    - Morris, Ivan Misunderstandings re Mishima Suicide, [n.p.], [1970], (4 page a.ms. (essay) ) (Box 41)
  - Subseries VIII.2: Arranged Correspondence
    - Alexander, Annalita, 1993-1998 (Box 42)
    - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc. 1956, 1961 (Box 42)
    - Amnesty International, 1970-1978, n.d. (Box 42)
    - B, 1967-1976 (Box 42)
    - C, 1976 (Box 42)
    - F, 1952-1970 (Box 42)
    - G, 1959, 1972 (Box 42)
    - H, n.d. (Box 42)
    - Jensen, Julie, n.d. (Box 42)
    - Kiddo, Anson, 1971-1972 (Box 42)
    - Kiddo, Anson, 1973-1974, n.d. (Box 42)
    - M, 1962-1976 (Box 42)
    - Morris, Edita, 8 May 1974 (Box 42)
    - Morris, Ivan, 1936-1969 (Box 42)
    - Morris, Ivan, 1970-1976, n.d. (Box 42)
    - Morris, Ivan: Condolence Letters, 1976 (Box 42)
    - Morris, Nobuko, 1971, n.d. (Box 42)
    - Nissenson, Hugh, 1975 (Box 42)
    - Oxford University Press, 29 Sept. 1960 (Box 42)
    - P, 1969 (Box 42)
    - R, 1969, 1976 (Box 42)
    - S, 1966-1975 (Box 42)
    - Tong, T. K. 20 May 1969 (Box 42)
    - V, 1965, 1973 (Box 42)
    - W, 1952, 1970 (Box 42)
    - Unidentified, 1966-1976, n.d. (Box 42)
  - Subseries VIII.3: Manuscripts
    - Morris, Ivan [?] "Animal Words", list, 25 May 1969 (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan "By the Sea of Japan", story, n.d. (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan "The Challenge of "Soka Gakkai"", article, published version appearing in Books & Writers, May 1966 (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan "Chess", notes, 1968-1969 (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] "Christmas Cards", lists, 1972-1975 (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] "Class Notes", n.d. (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] "Coca-Cola", collection of poetry, 1944 (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan "Comment on Darkness in Summer", book review, Oct. 1973 (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan "The "Demos" in Japan", paper, 14 June 1960 (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan "Economic Realism in the Later Works of Ihara Saikuku", paper, published version in The Transactions of the Asiatic Society of Japan, 3rd Series, Vol. VII, 1959 (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] "English Language Notes", 1967[?] (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan "L'évolution politique du Japon d'apres guerre", article, published version appearing in Politique Etrangere, June 1956, (langcode="fre">French) (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] "Fiction Non-Fiction Read", lists, 1940-1945 (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan "Foreign Policy Issue in the 1958 Elections", paper, 1958 (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan "Government I", exam blue book, 22 Jan. 1943 (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan I Remember Pearl Harbor, book jacket blurb, 1975 (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan "In Defense of Communism", essay, 28 Jan. 1942 (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan "Interview with Kobe Abe", transcript, Nov. 1969 (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan "Japanese Foreign Policy and Neutralism", paper, 1959[?] (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] "Library", list, 1967-1976 (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] "Losses", notes, 1967-1976, n.d. (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan, ed. Madly Singing in the Mountains: An Appreciation and Anthology of Arthur Waley, book jacket, n.d. (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] "A Man Who Rendered the Most Meritorious Services in the Meiji Restoration", translation of essay by Fukuzama Yukichi, n.d. (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] "A Meaningful Dialogue", play, fragment, n.d. (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] "Melancholia", collection of poetry, 1944 (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] Miscellaneous Notes, 1954-1976, n.d. (Box 43)
    - Morris, Ivan "The Moscow Negotiations and their Repercussions as Seen from Tokyo", article, Sept. 1956 (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] "Packing Lists", 1973-1974 (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan The Pillow Book of Sei Shonagan, translations, n.d. (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan The Pillow Book of Sei Shonagon, notes, n.d. (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan The Pillow Book of Sei Shonagon, advertisement, 1967 (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] "Poems", collection of poetry, 1944 (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan "The Policeman and the Student: Some Notes on the Political Scene in Japan", essay, n.d. (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] Prayers, n.d. (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan Research Notes, n.d. (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] "Reviews", list, n.d. (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] "Sentences", lists, n.d. (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan "The Setting", book, fragment, 1962[?] (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] "Socialist Merger in Japan", essay, n.d. (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan "Soka Gakkai Brings 'Absolute Happiness'", article, published version appearing in The New York Times Magazine, 18 July 1965 (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan "Some Aspects of the Tale of Genji Scroll", book, 1st draft, n.d. (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan "Soviet-Japanese Peace Treaty Talks: The Negotiations as seen from Tokyo", article, published version in The World Today, Aug. 1955 (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan "Spanish I", exam blue book, 19 March 1943 (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan "Sunny Greece", letter to the editor, published version, 20 June 1968 (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan "Swedish Course at the Lingauphone Institute", worksheets, 1976 (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan "Uncensored Reflections", 1944 (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] "U.S. and U.K. words", list, June 1969 (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] "Useful Words", list, n.d. (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan "Violence in Japanese Politics", introductory essay to special New Leader issue on Japan, 6 Nov. 1960 (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan "The World of "The Tale of the Genji"", book, chapters 1-4, Dec. 1961 (Box 44)
    - Morris, Ivan [?] Unidentified Fragments, 1966-1976, n.d. (Box 44)
    - Unidentified Unidentified Fragments: Calligraphy, n.d. (Box 44)
  - Subseries VIII.4: Notebooks
    - National Diary, 1941 (Box 44)
    - Address Book, 1972 (Box 44)
    - Address Book, 1976 (Box 45)
    - Address Book, 1976 (Box 45)
    - Guest Book for Reading of "The Green Card Romance", 3 Feb. 1988 (Box 45)
  - Subseries VIII.5: Documents
    - Agreement with Anthony Sheil Associates for the publication of The Lonely Monk and Other Puzzles, n.d. (Box 45)
    - Agreement with John Brown Publisher of the Oxford University Press for a book about Japan, 6 Nov. [n.y.] (Box 45)
    - Guest Book, loose pages, n.d. (Box 45)
    - Agreement with the Royal Institute of International Affairs for objective and systematic investigation of "The 'Reverse Course' in Japan", 13 Dec. 1955 (Box 45)
    - Agreement with UNESCO for English translation of Saikaku, 23 Dec. 1955, (langcode="fre">French) (Box 45)
    - Agreement with Delamain et Boutelleau for introduction, 2 March 1956, (langcode="fre">French) (Box 45)
    - Agreements for English translation of Fires in the Plains by Shohei Ooka, Aug. 1956 (Box 45)
    - Agreement with Shohei Ooka and Curtis Brown, Ltd. for English translation of Fires in the Plains, 14 Feb. 1957 (Box 45)
    - Agreement with Alfred A. Knopf, Inc. for English translation of The Golden Temple by Yukio Mishima, 20 March 1957 (Box 45)
    - Contract for English translations of Japanese short stories for the Anthology of Modern Japanese Short Stories, 1957-1959 (Box 45)
    - Contract for English translation of Saikuku, 17 Sept. 1958, (langcode="fre">French) (Box 45)
    - Cards of introduction for Ivan Morris, 1960 (Box 45)
    - Letter of appointment to Assistant Professor of Chinese and Japanese at Columbia University, 4 Apr. 1960 (Box 45)
    - Contract for the publication of The World of the Tale of Genji, 26 Aug. 1960 (Box 45)
    - Letter of appointment to Assistant Professor of Chinese and Japanese at Columbia University, 3 Apr. 1961 (Box 45)
    - Contract with UNESCO for English translation of Court Diaries of Medieval Japan, 6 June 1961 (Box 45)
    - Certificate of appointment to Associate Professor of Chinese and Japanese at Columbia University, 7 May 1962 (Box 45)
    - Agreement with Sidgwick and Jackson Ltd. for an untitled non-fiction book on Japan, 18 June 1962 (Box 45)
    - Agreement with D.C. Heath and Company for the publication of Japan 1931-1945--Militarism, Fascism, Japanism?, 4 Dec. 1962 (Box 45)
    - Agreement with Alfred A. Knopf, Inc. for the publication of The World of "The Tale of Genji, 16 May 1963 (Box 45)
    - Agreement with Columbia University Press for the publication of the Dictionary of Selected Forms in Japanese Literature, 20 Dec. 1965 (Box 45)
    - Cards of introduction for Ivan Morris, 1966 (Box 45)
    - Agreement with George Weidenfeld and Nicolson Ltd. for publication of The Samurai, 11 Jan. 1966 (Box 45)
    - Agreement with Thames and Hudson Ltd. for "The Far East", contribution to The Seventeenth Century, ed. Hugh Trevor-Roper, 8 March 1966 (Box 45)
    - Agreement with John Brown Publisher of Oxford University Press for the publication of The Pillow Book of Sei Shonagon, 4 May 1966 (Box 45)
    - Agreement with Columbia University Press for the publication of The Pillow Book of Sei Shonagon, 20 Jan. 1967 (Box 45)
    - Agreements for publication of Madly Singing in the Mountains: An Appreciation and Anthology of Arthur Waley, 1968 (Box 45)
    - Agreement with Thames and Hudson Ltd. for publication of A Concise History of Japan, 15 Aug. 1968 (Box 45)
    - Agreement with Walker Publishing Co., Inc. for publication of The Riverside Puzzles, 2 Dec. 1968 (Box 45)
    - Agreement with Anthony Sheil Associates for publication of Pillow Book Puzzles, 15 Jan. 1969 (Box 45)
    - Program from Dinner in Honor of Ivan Morris, 27 May 1969 (Box 45)